Melich, Tanya M.; Papers apap079
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Tanya M. Melich Papers
1912-2018
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap079
37.8 cubic ft.
The Tanya M. Melich Papers contain materials relating to the political landscape of the United states throughout the latter half of the twentieth century, as well as various social movements with a particular emphasis on Women's rights.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Tanya Melich initially donated her papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 1989. She made additional donations in 1990, 2002-2003, 2012, 2015-2019, and 2024.
Biographical Sketch
Tanya Melich was born in Moab, Utah on April 23, 1936. Her father, Mitchell Melich, was an active member of the Republican party and served in the Utah State Senate from 1942 to 1950. He ran for Congress in 1948, was the Republican nominee for Utah governor in 1964, served on the Republican National Committee for Utah from 1966 to 1968, and acted as solicitor for the United States Department of Interior from 1969 to 1973.
Tanya Melich attended the University of Colorado and received a B.S. in Political Science in 1958, graduating cum laude with departmental and general honors. She was also elected to Phi Betta Kappa. She then attended Columbia University, receiving a master's degree in Public Law and Government in 1961.
Melich worked as a newspaper reporter for The Salt Lake Tribune in the late 1950s. In 1956 she was a Ford Foundation Political Intern for the Republican gubernatorial candidate in Colorado. Her first campaign experience in New York occurred in 1959 when she helped Samuel Pierce's campaign for general sessions judge. She continued to work on state and national campaigns in various positions: 1961 Louis J. Lefkowitz for mayor, New York City; research director 1964 Mitchell Melich for governor, Utah; state campaign deputy director 1965 John V. Lindsay for mayor, New York City; director of research 1966 William J. Casey for Congress, New York; director of research 1966 Nelson A. Rockefeller for governor, New York; associate to the scheduling director 1968 Nelson A. Rockefeller for U.S. President; deputy director of national delegate unit 1969 John V. Lindsay for mayor, New York City; research consultant for Fioravanto Perrotta 1970 Charles Goodell Election Committee, New York; state chair of research 1972 Richard M. Nixon, New York City campaign for the Committee to Re-Elect the President; deputy campaign director 1977 Arch Gillies for City Council, New York City; campaign manager 1978 Perry Duryea for governor, New York; member, advisory committee 1978 Michael Roth for attorney general, New York; member, advisory committee 1982 Whitney North Seymour, Jr. for United States Senate, New York; state campaign manager 1989 Rudolf Giuliani for mayor, New York City; advisory committee.
In the early 1960s, Melich worked on the staff of the Foreign Policy Association, where she prepared information and analyses relating to special projects in Latin America. The Foreign Policy Association was, and remains, a national and nonprofit organization founded to educate Americans about international issues. Melich later worked for ABC-TV News in its election unit and was director of ABC-News National Election Research for the 1964 presidential election. Her work focused on conducting research for television and radio coverage of political events, particularly presidential politics. From 1975 to 1981 Melich worked in various positions for the Corporate Affairs division of CBS, Inc. At CBS she studied the impact of public policy issues on CBS. She also prepared and supervised the writing of opinion papers and reports during this time. In 1983, Melich went on to operate her own consulting business, Political Issues Management.
Melich has been heavily involved with several organizations relating to both political and social concerns over the last several decades. In the mid 1960s she became involved in the Ripon Society, a group concerned with the growing power of right-wing politicians in the Republican party. The Ripon Society has been described as, "a moderate Republican research and policy organization dedicated to a common sense, pragmatic system of governance." In 1974 she was elected the Ripon Society National Governing Board Chair.
Melich is considered one of the founders of the modern women's movement. In 1971 she helped organize the Manhattan Women's Political Caucus. She went on to co-found the New York State National Women's Political Caucus (NYS NWPC) in 1972. In 1973, she became affiliated with the National Women's Education Fund, the first organization designed to educate women on ways to gain political power. Melich served as the Fund's president from 1980 through 1983. Concerned with the treatment of women in American society, she wanted women's issues to have more of an impact on the Republican Party's agenda. In 1976 Melich co-founded the National Women's Republican Task Force and was instrumental in organizing the group New York State Republicans for Women's Issues. In 1984 she co-founded the New York State Republican Family Committee. Both of the organizations advocated the Republican Party to take a pro-choice stance and recognize the needs and concerns of women to a greater extent.
Melich has also served as a member of several organizations concerned with the political and social state of America. Such organizations include: the United States Civil Rights Commission New York State Advisory Board and the New York State Commission on Judicial Nomination. She also served on the advisory board of the White House Project, a project to "change biases against women's leadership ability, and foster the entry of women into positions of leadership, including the U.S. presidency."
Her writings have appeared in The New York Times, The Washington Post, Newsday, Daily News, USA Today Chicago Tribune, and the electronic publication Women's Enews. In addition to writing articles, Melich has also worked as writer, researcher, and/or editor on numerous books including: Jaws of Victory (Little Brown and Co. 1974), The Lessons of Victory (The Dial Press, 1969), Thomas E. Dewey on the American Political System, ABC News Fact Book for the 1964 presidential campaign, American Heritage State Series and Peace: The Control of National Power (Beacon Press, 1963). One of her most well-known works is The Republican War Against Women: An Insider's Report From Behind the Lines. Bantam Books published the title in 1996. It was described by The Washington Post as, "a powerful, evocative account of how social conservatives and Republican politicians have used the GOP to roll back the gains of the women's movement." The work received national attention from women's organizations and political groups. It was given the Gustavus Meyer Center Award as an outstanding book on human rights in North America.
Tanya Melich has received many other awards and honors for her work. She was honored by the Manhattan Women's Political Caucus as one of New York's outstanding women. She has received the New York NOW Susan B. Anthony Women of Achievement Award, the Alfred F. Moran Advocacy Award by Family Planning Advocates of New York, and was commemorated by the New York State National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL). She was a Woodrow Wilson Visiting Fellow, speaking on the United States political process and women. She has also been involved in civic, social, and political organizations such as Planned Parenthood-New York City Council of Advocates, New York City's Department of Cultural Affairs, and the Advisory Council of the Women's International Leadership of International House.
Scope and Contents
The Tanya M. Melich Papers document the political and societal landscape of the United States with materials primarily from the latter half of the twentieth century. Much of the material focuses on the Republican Party on both a national and local level (particularly New York City, where Melich resides). There is information relating to Republican platforms, election concerns, political organizations, and voter demographics. Melich has consistently been extremely interested in women's rights—especially reproductive rights—and collected many materials relating to this topic. She also conducted research in a variety of other areas including: affirmative action, poverty, the impact of technology on broadcast media, overpopulation concerns, and human rights more generally.
The Melich Papers include many types of materials including newspaper clippings, academic articles, magazine articles, reports, memos, correspondence, and publications of advocacy organizations. Although the majority of these items were produced by other individuals or organizations, there are some materials written by Melich, including articles, some correspondence, and administrative materials from her time as President of the National Women's Education Fund.
This collection is divided into fifteen series and was originally processed in 2003. Over the next ten years, Melich sent approximately fifteen additional cubic feet of records, which were interfiled with the original materials to create one complete collection. In 2021, sixty-six additional boxes were processed from Melich's most recent donation in 2019, and three additional series were created: The White House Project, Women's Advocacy, and the New York State Republican Family Committee.
Because the previously processed materials related to women's political and social rights were not rearranged with the new series in 2021, please see the Subject Files series for materials related to the ones found in the Women's Advocacy series.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Political Files, 1944-2015, Undated
Series 2 - Campaign Files, 1957-2018, Undated
Series 3 - ABC Election Research Unit, 1960-1965, Undated
Series 4 - CBS, Inc., 1961-2009, Undated
Series 5 - The Ripon Society, 1961-1998, Undated
Series 6 - New York City Partnership, 1981-1982, Undated
Series 7 - United States Commission on Civil Rights New York State Advisory Board, 1967-1984
Series 8 - International Women's Year, 1976-1978, Undated
Series 9 - Organizations, 1958-2016, Undated
Series 10 - Subject Files, 1944-2017, Undated
Series 11 - Publications, 1967-2007
Series 12 - Melich Publications, Speeches, and Editing Work, 1957-2007, Undated
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Public Servants; Ethnic Groups; Pro-choice Movement—United States; Political Campaigns—New York (State); Women's Rights; New York (State)—Politics and government; Articles; Interviews; Transcripts; Memorandums; Correspondence; Clippings; Official reports; Legislative Records; Melich, Tanya; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; University at Albany, State University of New York; United States Commission on Civil Rights; Ripon Society; Republican Party (U.S. 1854-)
- Political Files, 1944-2015; Undated; 1; 9.4 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The material in this series focuses primarily on the Republican Party candidates and platforms for national elections and elections in New York, both the state and city. There is also information relating to specific election and demographic concerns for the Republican Party. There is extensive documentation concerning Richard Nixon's U.S. presidential bids and the political realities of the early 1960s. In addition to specific elections, there are materials concerning the Republican Party more generally, such as its strengths and weaknesses and stances on particular social concerns. The News Clippings folders contain articles or entire pages of newspapers encompassing elections, editorials, Republican and Democratic platforms and candidates. Not all the clippings have been photocopied; the originals are often brittle and should be handled with care. The material is arranged by date of its creation. For example, documents created in 1963 regarding the 1964 election are in the folders for 1963. Researchers interested in a particular election year should look in the folders of the prior year for pre-election reports, analysis, news stories, relevant correspondence, etc. It is also recommended that researchers look in the Campaign series for additional material related to a specific candidate, election, or platform.
  - Richard and Pat Nixon, Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 1)
  - 1956 Republican Convention (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 2)
  - Democratic Party Publications, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 3)
  - Richard M. Nixon, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 4)
  - Richard Nixon, Newspaper Clippings, 1956-1959 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 5)
  - "The 1958 Elections: Summary Report" (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 6)
  - New York, 1958 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1958 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 9-10)
  - News Clippings, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 11)
  - 1960 Republican Convention, 1959-1960; Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 12)
  - Election 1960—Kennedy v. Nixon and Aftermath, 1959-1961; Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Information on Republicans, 1959-1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 14)
  - New York, 1959-1960 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 15)
  - New York—Democrats, 1959-1968 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 16)
  - Republican Stengths/Weaknesses in Various Locations, 1959-1975; Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 17)
  - Democratic Party—Newspaper Clippings, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 18)
  - Legislative Reapportionment (1964-1966), 1960; 1962-1965 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 19)
  - New York—Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 20)
  - Richard M. Nixon, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 21)
  - Nixon—Newspaper Clippings, ca. 1960s (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 22)
  - Election, 1961 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 23)
  - New York, 1961 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 24)
  - New York "GOP in New York City" Candidates Kit, 1961 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 25-27)
  - Barry Goldwater—Presidential Campaign, 1962-1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 28-29)
  - Election Reports, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 30)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 31)
  - Nixon—Newspaper Clippings, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 32)
  - New York, 1962-1963 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 33)
  - The 1962 Elections, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 34)
  - News Clippings, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 35)
  - Surveys (1964 election) Arkansas, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 36)
  - Surveys (1964 election) Maine, Massachusetts, Vermont, New Hampshire, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 37)
  - Barry Goldwater—Election Strategy, 1963-1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 38)
  - Election 1964—"Congressional Quarterly", 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 39)
  - Election 1964—Electoral Strategy, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 40)
  - Wallace—Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 41)
  - Barry Goldwater, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 42)
  - Barry Goldwater—Supporters and Staff, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 43)
  - Goldwater—Pre-Convention Delegates, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 44)
  - Barry Goldwater "FACT", 1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 45)
  - Democratic Party—Newspaper Clippings, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 46)
  - General File, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Political Files), Folder 47)
  - "National Review", 1964 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 1)
  - New York, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 2)
  - New York—Newspaper Clippings, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 5)
  - Election 1964—General, 2001; Undated (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 6)
  - Election 1964—Results, 1964-1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 7)
  - Election 1964—Rockefeller on Issues, Particularly Goldwater (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 8)
  - Republicans after Goldwater Defeat, 1964-1965; 1967; Undated (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 9)
  - 1968 Republican Convention, 1964; 1967-1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 10)
  - 1964 Election of John Lindsay, 1964-1966; 1969 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 11)
  - John Lindsay, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 12)
  - John Lindsay—Press Releases, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 13)
  - "National Review", 1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 14)
  - New York, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 15-16)
  - New York—Newspaper Clippings, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 17-18)
  - New York—Voting Statistics, Assessments, SES Breakdown Polls, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 19)
  - Ronald Reagan through 1968, 1965-1968; Undated (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 20)
  - John Lindsay—Post Election, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 21)
  - John Lindsay—Post Election, Swizzle Stick, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 22)
  - Misc., 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 23)
  - New York, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 24)
  - New York—Newspaper Clippings, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 26)
  - Nixon, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 27)
  - "Rally", 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 28)
  - Rockefeller—Newspaper Clippings, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 29)
  - Romney, 1966 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 30)
  - 1968 Republican Convention, 1967-1968; Undated (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 31)
  - Election 1968—"Congressional Quarterly Weekly Report-Special Report Presidential '68", 1967 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 32)
  - "Battle Line", 1967 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 33)
  - "Memo from Cope", 1967 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 34)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 35)
  - Nixon, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 36)
  - Wallace, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 37)
  - 1968 Republican Convention and Aftermath, Undated (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 38)
  - 1968 Republicans—Liberal, 1972; 2001; Undated (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 39)
  - Political Files—Barry Goldwater, Newspaper Clippings, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 40)
  - "Battle Line", 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 41)
  - Conventions 1968—"Congressional Quarterly, Weekly Report-Convention Guide" (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 42)
  - Democratic Party, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 43)
  - Elections—Lindsay, Newspaper Clippings, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 44)
  - "Memo from Cope", 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 45)
  - Nixon, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 46-49)
  - Nixon—Newspaper Clippings, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 50)
  - Notes—Voting Records, 1968 (Box 2 (1-Political Files), Folder 51)
  - News Clippings, 1968 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 1-2)
  - New York, 1969 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 3)
  - Republican National Convention, 1968 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller, 1968 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 5)
  - New York—"1969 Annual Report of the Board of Elections in the City of New York" (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 6)
  - New York—Newspaper Clippings, 1969 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 7)
  - "The 1958 Elections: Summary Report", 1969 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 8)
  - Richard Nixon—"The Nixon Administration January- May, 1969" (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 9)
  - Richard Nixon—"The Nixon Administration January-August, 1969" (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 10)
  - Richard Nixon—"The Nixon Administration, Economic and Social Policies", 1969 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 11)
  - Richard Nixon—Inauguration Invitation, 1969 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 12)
  - Richard Nixon Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 13)
  - New York—Newspaper Clippings, ca. 1970s (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 14)
  - Democratic Party—Newspaper Clippings, 1972 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 15)
  - Democratic Party—Newspaper Clippings, 1972 (Box 3 (1-Political Files), Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 1972 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 1-2)
  - Nixon—Inauguration Invitations, 1972 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings (The New York Times Magazine July 22, 1973) (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 4)
  - Nixon, 1974 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller, 1974 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 6)
  - Election Maps, 1975 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 7)
  - Congression Jack Kemp, 1978-1979; 1987; Undated (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 8)
  - New York—Republican County Committee, 1980 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 9)
  - Senator Patrick Moynihan Newsletters, 1984-1994 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 10)
  - Pat Moore—65th AD 1986 GOP Candidate, 1986-1987; Undated (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 11)
  - Election 1992—"TCC Journal" (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 12)
  - Charles Millard for Congress, 1993-1994; Undated (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 13)
  - Midterm Election 1994—Women in Politics, 1993-1995 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 14)
  - Mark Green—Public Advocate for the City of New York, 1994-1995; 1999 (Box 4 (1-Political Files), Folder 15)
- Campaign Files, 1957-2018; Undated; 2; 5.4 cubic ft.
  These files contain material relevant to the specific campaigns for candidates either in New York State or national elections. While Series one is a collection of Melich's external research, this series contains information on campaign initiatives Melich was personally involved with. There are publications, campaign brochures (for either Republican or Democratic candidates), form letters, notes, correspondence, and reports within this series, many written by or for Melich. Some of the files include position papers, outlining a number of topics of importance to the election and a summary of the candidates' position.
  This series features information related to Nelson Rockefeller's U.S. presidential campaign, including delegate files compiled for each state. These folders incorporate basic information regarding the political structure of states such as the names and addresses of Governor, Republican Campaign headquarters, and material related to the delegates for the 1968 Republican Convention. There is also information from The Committee for the Re-Election of the President (perjoratively referred to as "CREEP"), with materials concerning the campaign to elect Richard M. Nixon to a second term.